So lecture three is about verification.
In the last lecture when we talked about
uh inference time scaling and the
generation
verification gap. Uh basically what we
discussed was that language model seems
to be able to um seems to know the
answer to many of the hard questions um
and especially with methods such as
repeated sampling or other scaling test
test time techniques. they can generate
one but a question is how do they how
can we automatically select which answer
is correct or guide the model throughout
the process of answer generation. So
that leads us to verification where
which we are learning about today. Um so
in today's lecture we are going to learn
about the following four paper papers
and it kind of there is a progression of
like how our uh kind of the way we
approach verification changed or
progressed throughout the years. Uh so
let's first start with training
verifiers to solve math for problems.
This is a paper uh from OpenAI in 2021
and the motivation for this work was
that LLM hallucinate and um can
confidently present wrong solutions to
the users. Uh this still is true to this
day. Four years later, of course, the
model has have become significantly
better. Um there is also at the time one
of the contributions of this paper was
to introduce a new reasoning benchmark
the around math and you can see here in
blue one of these uh problems. Um this
is um this is a uh this is the type of
problem that um at the time it was hard
for LLMs to solve and uh this led to
this new data set and and and and that
that is has become kind of a a a a big
part of many of the benchmarking task
for LLMs and even to this day this data
set is called GSM8K and even to this
date um for smaller models and
benchmarking it's still a very useful
language modeling evaluation and you can
consider it for the type of evals that
you want to define on your projects as
well. So um it basically consists of
8,500
grade school math problems. uh and the
goal with was this for this was to have
uh the quality and diversity of the
problems but also importantly there was
a focus on multi-step reasoning meaning
that to solve the problems even though
the problems were uh simple but the the
model required a few steps of reasoning
to get to the answer. Um
and and you could also collect u the
solution in natural language uh as
opposed to uh pure math. Um but the
other contribution of this paper which I
which we're going to spend more time on
was to train a verification model where
the verifier outputs the probability
that a solution is correct. So let's see
about how this can be useful. For
example, the model jet the when as
humans we solve problems, it would be
very very good for us to have access to
kind of a rubric or a way for us to tell
whether we are correct or not. And we
kind of want to provide the same thing
through this verifier for the language
model.
So now how these verif the the the
verifier was trained in this case is
that assume that we have a question and
a solution for it. Then we do have a
label whether the it's a binary label
whether it's correct or incorrect. And
during the training process the
generator the language model which is in
charge of uh answering questions here uh
produces SI which is the solution to
question QI. Um and then we can generate
do repeated sampling and generate
multiple in this case 100 solutions per
problem. And then we create these labels
based on whether they were correct or
not. Um remember that these questions
and answers were selectively designed by
a lot of manual human supervision. So we
know what the answers the final answers
to these problems are. So we can just
based on that create these labels for
these problems. Um and then given that
we can train a verifier because now we
have a we have a question we have a
solution and then we have a label for
it. Um
um now the way we use it at test time is
that at test time again we generate a
lot of answers and then we use the
verifier and look at the score the
basically the log probability that is in
this model now to see which one has a
higher score and use that for as our f
and show that as our final answer. Um
so in this paper the verifier was
trained not just based on the
correctness prediction but there was
also a language modeling uh objective.
So the language modeling objective is
also like given uh for example here
given these tokens corresponding to the
questions. The moment we get to the
solution solution token we also add a
loss that kind of urges like motivates
the model to predict or reduce the the
solution um kind of um
uh distance from the true labels for
that solution. So in this paper they
said that it helped them to have two
losses. One is the binary loss and the
other one was the the normal language
modeling uh next prediction token loss.
Um and the verifier itself the
architecture of the verifier is also a
language model. Um but also this
language model has a small scalar head
that outputs the binary prediction
um on a per token basis. So basically on
a per token we are saying how close was
the solution to the to the true labels
uh generated by humans.
Um and then the tokens in questions are
masked out because we are not optimizing
for that. So we generate the question we
pass in fill in the model with the
questions and we ask it to generate the
solutions and we we work with these two
losses. Um
the way they trained the model was to
fine-tune the generator language model
for two epochs. Um and then sample a 100
completions per question um label it
whether they were correct or not and
then train a verifier uh for a single
epoch on this data set. So first they
did fine-tune the language model on a s
on that data set on a portion of that
data set. Um, and this step maybe
it's like debatable whether we we still
need this this step or not because
language models are already very good at
instruction following and understanding
math. So maybe and for a lot of newer
verifiers we directly go to the training
the verifier objective without any
supervised fine-tuning first.
Um, so they did a number of abilation
studies. one was to create this label of
correct or incorrect at the sentence
level. Um so
we have a loss that only concerns at
each sentence level for example after
each period looks into the previous
sentence and looks whether this is a
correct step given the steps of the
correct step for the for the solution or
not. or they could do at a token level.
So this is like very a very noisy kind
of label like basically we want every
token to follow um the the the the
pattern that leads to a final correct
solution at the end of this generation.
Um and then the way this is used at test
time is the final solution score is the
score after the last token. Because if
you have a token label prediction per if
you have a label prediction per token at
the end of the day we only we want only
one prediction for the entire generation
whether it's correct or not. And it
turns out in this case they looked it
after the last token. All right. So we
were talking about if you have a token
per a label per token at the end of the
day we just we want one token yes or no
whether this answer was correct or not
and um this is done in this case by just
looking at the very last token and if
that was a correct then it's the entire
answer is assumed correct and otherwise
uh it's assumed incorrect. So we predict
for S1 S2 uh SM we predict these labels
and then we only look at the very last
label for the to generate and allocate a
label for the entire solution.
So um here is um looking back at these
problems um when we get to the solution
we are looking at the token level
prediction by the trained verifier and
if it's green means the verifier has a
high score and the red ones means a low
score in this case and in this case this
was there were some lower scores in the
middle but towards the end it become
became greener and greener and this was
a correct prediction at the end at the
end the last the very last stage is a
green one and we assume the actual score
and the verifier predictions are um and
in in this case are matching. In this
other case uh the last verifier is red.
Uh it starts off well but it has a there
is something that a mistake is made um
which I
uh
which is uh towards the the end of this
generation step and the actual score is
negative and the verifier prediction is
also negative. So this is how basically
this verifier is trained for GSM8K and
then they did some abilations or uh
comparisons with a baseline where we
just directly just fine-tune on this
data set. Um finetune meaning with
supervised fine tuning. So we just take
the base model and the next token bird
prediction or we do this verification
stage uh where we generate a 100 samples
uh at each at each generation and use
the highest score of the verifier as the
true as the delivered output by our
system. So the the idea to what we can
see here is that um for both 6B and
1775B
models the this one is a GPT3 model I
believe um for both of these
verification seems to work better
especially as the training set size for
the verifier increases. So, so this the
verifier model eventually outperform the
fine-tuning uh only uh approach.
Um and vice versa if you have smaller
data sets in this case less than a
thousand for the 175B
uh we um the verification is not helping
much.
Sorry, but what can you speak up? Um
like the test score rate um um I mean it
has a sol of the 6B verification um is
still much higher than the
on smaller bit
like the orange still like
>> isn't it lower? Okay, I see.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Um, let me go here. So, this is
another result which which is very
interesting and some this is something
that could potentially be a research
project that you guys can look into. So,
what they did is that they tested two
idea two approaches. One having a larger
generator and smaller verifier and two
having a smaller generator and larger
verifier. And what they saw was that the
larger generator helps with a smaller
wave does better than vice versa. And to
some extent this is intuitive, right?
Because if we assume generation is
naturally or on an ex like um on average
is a harder task than verification, then
this this might make sense. But like
finding the parto optimal of like how
these two can um kind of be the sizes
with respect to each other would be a
very interesting um pro research
direction question especially right now
as the base model or generators have
improved a lot and also we have access
to a lot of verifiers on hugging face
there's like there's a leaderboard of
like verification verifier models or
reward models that can be tested against
um So um again uh this was the main
message from this this uh abilation
study.
Another result that uh about test time
uh scaling that they they're showing is
that as they increase the number of
completions per problem and then they
use the verifier it seems like around
400 or so the verifier
that's that's where they get a lot of
benefit but after that they're not
getting a lot of benefit. So if they
sample 800 uh solutions and they use the
verifier against that the verifier kind
of fails to track what's best and what's
not compared to the true true kind of
distribution of the of the solutions. So
um the uh one question for you is that
do you remember last time when we talked
about majority voting what was the range
that we were getting out of that? Like
we show that majority voting although is
useful to some extent as we increase the
number of samples per query it fails
after some point to track and that's the
generation verification gap. Does any
does anyone remember that?
Okay. Uh so that was we saw that the
failure happens after 10 to like we
never got to 50 samples like even though
the coverage goes up the the pass at one
or basically how we can generate select
the correct response uh fails for around
50 or less for the majority voting
approach. But here they're showing that
up until 400 they can increase the
accuracy and their verifier is still
useful.
Yes, but these uh but the but when they
they have so they do have the true
labels per problem and then when they
are testing this verifier the verifier
ranks these uh at each point say for 400
these 400 solutions they they take the
highest score and they compare that
against ground truth and that's what
they're reporting here whether that was
correct or not.
83 times performance monitor completion
>> at test time and training time as well
for the verifier but not for the
generator.
>> Okay. for the training types all are
human
for the training like
>> there there's only so for each problem
the human has once generated an answer
that's offline that's done once then you
take the model generate a 100 solutions
per problem and you compare each of the
solutions against the ground truth which
which is generated only once by humans
and you see whether they match or not
that's how you create the label
Okay.
Okay. Any questions from this paper?
Yes.
>> Question for it makes sense. It's the
verifier is increasing result but after
that why does it drop like intuitively
like why doesn't it stay constant?
>> Okay. So the question is why does it
drop after a after 400? It shouldn't be
constant because we are not showing the
coverage. If you're showing the output
of this entire system where the verifier
ranks these say at this point 800
different solutions and we are getting
the max score of the verifier but the
precision of the verifier drops like
it's like if two solution are too close
to each other but one is correct and
incorrect at across 800 it can't like
distinguish between the two as well as
it could do for 400. Right? So, so
that's where we get the drop in
accuracy. And in reality, when they're
outputting their they they created this
system, they said that we stopped at uh
they stopped at 100 samples because
that's where they get most of the gains
anyway and that's where they're
consistent
>> repeated sound. So parallel.
>> So same question you ask the model 100
different times to solve that.
>> Yes.
>> When they generate the label sentences,
how do you distinguish like like one can
just be a paraph?
Because this is trained on a larger data
set and because the the verifier and
they consider both sentence based and
token based it still works because the
data that the trainer first of all the
verifier is a language model itself. So
it knows a lot about this space itself
but also through this uh label training
it has been trained to be able to
distinguish between correct and
incorrect.
>> Yes.
>> Uh does it make sense because I'm
standing on the verification itself?
>> So the question let me repeat the
questions because one of you asked this
before. So the question is does it make
sense to scale the verifier? do test
time scaling on the verifier. Yes. And
we're going to see that in the in the
future slides.
>> Yes.
>> Um the you showed like verification
versus fine tuning. You showed that like
before like around like a thousand steps
like thousand like training size, right?
Um the fine tuning actually does better
than the verified. Does that happen
again? Like if you scale like to higher
>> um the verifi finetuning versus
verification, do they cross each other?
>> Yeah, I get
>> um
like if you were to actually if you do
need that much data for for for example
for one for a task.
I mean I think they would like if you
have a ton of data like at a a whole lot
of data then fine-tuning and
verification probably they're going to
be the same going to kind of converge to
the same thing. But the but the beauty
of a verifier is that you are not
fine-tuning your base language model.
You're not making it like really custom
to like one data set or one specific
task. So that base model the generator
model remains general and then now you
have a verifier that you can um kind of
lead the the langu the the base model.
Okay.
Um now let's go through the second
paper. Uh another paper by openai. Um
let's verify step by step.
And
so this was this came about a couple
years like less than two years after
that first paper. Again pro LLMs have
had the same challenges. They
hallucinated.
um if you if they're solving a problem
step by step and they make a step in a
single in in an S step early on it can
derail the entire answer right uh so the
solution that they were proposing here
is that um they consider these two kind
of approaches to reward modeling one is
outcome uh based reward model and the
other is processbased reward model so
the outcomebased one like we saw earlier
earlier in the previous paper it
generates a reward to the entire
solution. It's about the correctness of
the solution uh of the entire solution
whereas the process one um assigns a
different reward per step of the
optimization problem.
And so let's take a look exactly how
this training can be done for the OM
versus PRM. So we have a math problem.
The generator instead of generating a
100 solutions like it uh uh right now we
are only looking into a one solution and
it has a bunch of steps. Step one, two
and all the way until we get to the
final answer. Um and then we have the
ground truth. So we can um know whether
the final answer is correct or not
because we can match the final answer
against the ground truth. Um now with
ORM we are done there because we we
that's how we assigned the label for for
the model but for PRM uh the way they
did it in this paper was that they
looked into they had human annotators go
through the steps of the generations
um by the model and assign a score to
each step. So step one in this case was
correct. Step two was correct and
probably because the uh the uh maybe all
of these steps were correct. That's why
we we let it led to the final correct
answer. But basically they created this
entire data set of human annotated uh
stepwise kind of correct or incorrect
labels.
Um and the final reward for this
step-wise now can again in this case
could be what they propose is that could
can be calculated as the product of the
the stepwise rewards per step of the
model. So they basically train a model
against this step-wise annotations and
then they use that they create steps
like you can even ask the model to
generate the answers to a solution step
by step. So the steps are clear. They
run this PRM against each of those step.
They get a score. They multiply them
with each other. They they get a range
of like um what the the quality of the
answer and they can based on that they
can uh decide whether they uh output the
answer or try again. Um so this is
called process supervision. Um obviously
there is this credit assignment and then
it's the more precise way of collecting
uh data and assigning labels to
different steps of the problem rather
than just looking at the output answer.
Um
a property here that's very important
actually this is like a really kind it
could be a pitfall for uh test time
scaling is that with processor
supervision we can manage the false
positives way better than we can do with
just outcome supervisions supervision.
Why? Because model might hallucinate and
this happens surprisingly model can
hallucinate and get to a final correct
answer while the process for it is like
really wrong.
Whereas with process supervision because
we are kind of pro like we are
supervising we are seeing all the steps
and we have a score for it. It's less
likely that we get into that um mode
where the steps are wrong but we are uh
the final answer is correct.
Um also it encourages interpretable
reasoning and um human endorsed uh
process of solutions. It's human
endorsed again because humans have
created the labels. Um so this paper
produced this data set PRM 800K.
Um it's an open-source data set uh of
800K step level labels. So, so and and
um
so the way they did this was a generator
model against a language they took a
language model and they generated a
large number of samples per problem in a
step-wise matter manner and then they
also did this trick of like because they
wanted to collect higher quality
stepwise labels, they took him to um
what they call convincing wrong uh uh
kind of answers meaning that the they
gave higher pri priority to samples
where the the final answers were um
correct but the intermediate steps were
incorrect. Um
and this enabled them to be 2.6 times
more data efficient just than just
randomly selecting these samples and
give it to humans. So they did
iteratively. So they had like a very you
can have a step a PRM by just asking an
LLM to judge a step, right? You can have
that. Uh so they iteratively upgraded
the PRM by collecting this data and then
training on the PRM for it and then um
increasing the quality of the data. So
um and at each step the label was that
was collected was either positive or
negative or neutral. For example, let's
take a look at this problem. Uh the
denominator of a fraction is 7 less than
um uh 3 * the the numerator. If the
fraction is equivalent to 2 over 5, what
is the numer numerator of the fraction?
And then there are these steps and the
first step was labeled correct, second
was correct and all the way to the fifth
step was correct. U but this last step
obviously the model failed to do the
math. X should be 15 14 but it's seven.
So that was labeled incorrect. So that's
how they
collected the labels.
Um here is the process. So they took
GPT4 as their base model. Um [snorts]
they still fine-tune GPT4 for both the
OM and PRM training on this data set
first. So the supervised
uh uh finetuning first
uh
and
for OM of course they just have the
pairs of generated samples and final
correctness but for PRM they had this
generator generate the sample and then
the stepwise corre correctness label. Uh
for OM the final score was the score of
the final token in the completion. again
they again went to the token level
approach for ORM um but for PRM it was
the product of uh probabilities
uh for every stop now let's take a look
at some of the solutions um they were
showing that PRM outperforms OM and
majority voting so again here n is the
number of solutions per problem majority
voting again fails after in this case
100 or so samples Uh the blue line is
the OM model and the orange one is the
PRM approach that is doing better. Um
and the but they notice that PRM detects
correct solutions for some of the very
rare kind of occurrences of correct
answers on problems with less than 5%
correct answers in the distribution of
samples.
Um
they also showed the benefit of larger
data and this active learning uh
approach that they had.
Again um the
and and the other the other kind of
observation that they were showing is
that PRM seems to be more data
efficient. So the number of labels that
they collected for PRM if they match
that against um uh OM u both PRM and ORM
benefit from more and more labels but it
turns out that the PRM is more sample
efficient right so um so if they have
100 solutions label labeled per problem
for an OM model that's kind of like
having
like one solution per problem based on
the PRM approach and so on.
Um the other interesting property uh and
that's what what we all should strive as
we gener as we are training these kind
of verifier and reward model is the
gener generalizability
to new domains and new data sets. Uh
here what they're showing is that
majority voting actually is better than
OM in terms of how it generalizes. Uh
but PRM is a better u is a better than
majority voting overall. Um and uh it
can tolerate a whole lot more
distribution shift than majority voting.
Um and so overall this seems like a much
better approach here.
Um any questions?
Yes,
>> PRM obviously like could lead to like
false credit assignment if like a step
looks good but doesn't actually
contribute to the final answer. Are
there domains that you would expect PRM
to actually hurt?
>> Um so the question is can PRM hurt
sometimes because um the final answer
might still be incorrect. Um so the
truth is like a lot of the newer
approaches combine the two like the
reality is they combine both the PRM and
OM based solutions because you want to
get the bene benefit of of both
approaches. Um and the other thing is
that like the threshold that you can
define for for a PRM then is also like a
hyperparameter that now you have
introduced that you have to like deal
with and optimize for your system and
that that's an additional complexity
here but yes
>> the previous one
um does it make sense to this comparison
because J requests much more labels than
RN so does it show up where the access
Texas access is like nimble.
Um I think they were trying to Yeah,
because they also mentioned that it's
hard to compare and they did they did
manage to like have because um it's true
OM needs like K labels per problems but
PRM needs K times some number of steps
but then it's very hard to control that
number of steps of like how do you
exactly control but they did try to
manage that and I believe some of the
graphs they they do that but that's a
good Right. Yes.
>> Majority voting mean in this context.
>> So majority voting is you have n sample
you uh you don't have any access to any
reward model. You just see which sample
or solution is repeated most and you
take that as your final answer.
>> Are you also working on the reason
process?
>> No, you look into the final answer.
Um, in this case, are they using the
same PRM 800K for all of those tasks or
are they using different terms for each?
>> Um, because they're talking about
generalization, I assume this should be
>> the same
>> the same one. But yeah,
>> yes.
>> Uh, how does this avoid when the
reasoning is actually bad but rated
high? Like for example um if you go back
to slide
>> this one
>> yeah this one like what if like the uh
reasoning is let's call the numerator x
and then x = to 14 and it jumps immunity
to the x how does that avoid like 31
>> so you're saying the prm can give a high
score
>> like what if it's like skip all the
reasoning
um like let's call the numerator x and
then x= to 14 like how does that avoid
like that kind of hacking?
>> Sorry, I don't get it. Can you speak up
what's the alternative scenario you're
talking about?
uh like the the reasoning step would
just be numerator x and then x= 4 and
how does the like the PRM avoid the kind
of like real typing scenario
directly skip some steps and directly
generate the answer
like speed
>> so the parents are trained like parents
can also see the previous steps like the
questions previous step and here is the
current steps to score Right. You're
right. Um, so if X is 14, then it's
great, right?
>> It doesn't really encourage like the
thinking process of like going to step
by step.
>> It doesn't. No,
>> no, it doesn't. But you can prompt the
model to to do this cuz you're not
changing the model, right? You're not
changing your generator. You can't like
uh the that failure mode could be when
you were fine-tuning your generator
model and the model kind of stops
reasoning and just generates and final
answer that the PRM likes, right? But
you're not touching your generator. The
generators can still be prompted to do
reasoning, create these steps, and then
the verifier just scores them.
Um
>> but if let's say we want to use the PRM
to train the
>> yeah then you have to be careful then
you have to like make sure that the
chain of thought makes sense right and
your PRM again your PRM can the way you
train your PRM can also be aware of that
because your PRM could be as your your
PRM these are like human generated
labels in this case right if we had like
skipped all of this and then we would go
to X14. Probably the human says this is
this doesn't make sense. This step is
lower because this step is skipping a
few kind of reasoning steps.
Does that make sense? So these labels
are created by humans here.
>> So if the labels are not generated by
humans and we're going to see that in
the next paper. Yes, that is definitely
a caveat like and something that you can
make sure but there are ways to handle
that as well. Okay, so for now let's
assume these are human labels. So the
processes are labeled in a way that they
make sense as well. We have so many
things to encourage these gener
generation to make sense. First of all
the generator
should should generate the steps. The
PRM is trained on human annotations that
also they also make sure that this step
makes sense given the prior steps.
Any other questions?
Okay, let's go through the next the next
paper. Matt Shepard verify and reinforce
LLM step by step without human
annotation. So we're getting to what if
we um didn't want to collect that many
annotations
um from humans. So again motivation is
that um
having stronger vifiers shows the
potential to really improve models
reasoning behavior especially if you do
test time scaling. um PRM have shown
more potential than OMS but they require
a lot of data and it's hard to collect
these data so can be um automate the
process of label collection for PRMS
um so this paper talks about two kind of
approaches one is automatic annotation
um and also
u kind of brings the the the the reward
model as a into the loop of uh generator
optimization via a reinforcement
learning approach uh which uh we are
going to briefly mention that. So
in this case u the way they tried to go
about this um automatic kind of
annotation of steps was that they define
the quality of the reason step as the
potential of the step to reach to the
final correct answer. So let's say we
have we are at a given step. we sample n
kind of completions from that given step
and see the potential for um a correct
solution at the very end. So and they
introduce two ways of doing this. One is
the hard estimate uh where the the step
is annotated u as a success if
it any of those n generations after that
step gets to a final correct answer. The
soft estimate thinks of measures the
frequency like what portion of the
generations after a current step reached
the final correct answer. So here is
like how it works. um say here is the
problem and this is our current state.
Instead of just sampling one step, we
sample n is three in this case. So we
sample three steps and then we continue
um and and we measure the frequency in
the soft estimate. We we measure the
frequency of correct answer at the very
end. In hard estimate, we see whether
any any of these um uh are correct or
not. So hard estimate would be one for
step one. Soft estimate would be 2/3 for
step one.
Um anyone can
um kind of name it a challenge or a
drawback of this approach. So basically
the this soft or hard um kind of
estimation is replacing the human
annotations. So we're getting a score
per step by just rolling out more
samples from that step and and seeing
whether we reach to the final correct
answer or not and assume that we do have
final labels for these problems. Um
>> yes
>> or um where are predictable paths on the
lower right uh the when the
unpredictable path could be the only way
to solve
>> sorry speak up again if it's
unpredictable
>> unpredict or like unusual approaches to
solving a problem but it could be scored
as low or something that might You know
a way to be able to solve that problem.
So it might be really hard problem
to lose that path to that solution.
>> That is correct. So basically say n is
three here. Maybe we needed like 100 n
equal 100 to see that final correct kind
of like trajectory to score this step.
But we won't see that if we just look
into three, right? And then we give a
score of zero. Um, anything else?
>> Yes,
>> I guess this is similar, but if you're
dealing with like a hard question, if
you're taking the approach of like
generating a lot of samples, a lot of
the samples can just not be correct or
not the correct way to do it. So,
>> you just
>> you don't get any signal for hard
problems in this case.
>> Um, that's right.
that service doesn't mean any
>> exactly I think this is like probably
like these two that you all mentioned
here one is for hard problems you don't
get signal the other one is what if
there are like wrong steps in the middle
and we got to the final correct solution
um we still label those uh steps as
correct
um so the hope is that if you have more
samples it shows the wrongness in one of
these these kind of uh trajectories but
it's not guaranteed.
So um
so here is the verification process. You
sample and again you sample in candidate
solutions uh score them using the PRM
and you select the highest kind of PRM
score across across the the generated
samples. They also took this PRM and
trained the model with this PRM to
encourage the model to generate uh steps
that are scored higher and higher by
PRM. So PRM basically uh served as the
reward model uh for this. Um so for they
looked into the hard versus soft
annotations and although the loss
function um as they increased n would be
um it seemed like the the the soft
annotations were uh doing better. Uh but
somehow um what they observed with that
with an n equal 4 the depth of like the
trajectory completions to collect these
labels that's where they get like their
best results anyway. So it really didn't
matter whether they used the hard
estimate or softest estimate and they
went with the hard estimate at the very
end because it's um because it was just
easier to to measure that. So um
here is another comparison with
baseline. So here they have SC is major
self-consistency is another name for
majority voting which which solution was
most consistent. Uh that's the red one.
Um OM is the blue one and the shepherd
is this PRM approach uh is uh the green
one. And the interesting part here was
that there was no human annotation. All
the annotations were uh modeled
generated
um or the with the the mechanism that
they introduced.
Um here they also compare with PRM 800K
which was the way fire the that we that
in the previous paper that was trained
and it outperformed that as well on math
which is like a harder much harder uh
setup. This data set is more difficult
than GSM GSMHK and they were getting
even higher uh delta in there.
Uh they also compared the these results
uh with uh different types of verifiers
again across uh
GSM8K and MAT 500 problems. And you can
see that the difference between these
models and like these approaches um and
um there there is a notable difference
between these models and uh the
baselines which is self-consistency
approaches
and this is true across different models
70 lama 70B LMAD 34B and deepseek 67B
uh they also showed that they can get
even better they can make the model even
better if they they RL the model against
the PRMS that they trained. So in this
case the match sheepard on this their
their approach basically mis taking
mistral 7B this model and then they uh
po it against this PRM uh they're
getting much higher results u compared
to um doing this RL with just an OM um
the delta here is um slightly less I
would say than just the test time
scaling but um this is also
another way for the models to
self-improve, right? You generate the
annotation by the model itself. You
train the PRM and then use that PRM to
improve the mo the generator model as
well, both at test time and during with
this RL fine-tuning. So, it's like
multiple levels of using the model
itself to generate data and like RL
reward signal for for for itself.
Um
yeah and then they can do RL and PO and
do verification up on top and they get
even better results but it seems like
kind of kind of their optimizations are
plateauing at some point. Um any
questions from this paper?
>> Yes. Are there ways to build PRM that
like incentivize like self error
correction which I imagine be like a
desirable thing but like if we're only
you know rewarding each step be correct
you don't necessarily end up reinforcing
a lot of incorrect steps back
>> so encourage parents to do more self
correction
>> yes absolutely like for example one of
the methods that that can be done is
that you have a rubric or a set of rules
that you give the model as your scoring
step. So the model can check the step
against this rubric that your design for
this data set and that can be used as
extra signal whether this step makes
sense or not
right for example the very or like use a
calculator in that case in the problem
in the equation that we are seeing if
the model could use could do tool use or
use a calculator in that case it would
not it could solve that problem easily
right could for example use uh simp.
So, so there are ways to bring more
supervision and more signal and enable
the model to use tools and test time
scaling and agentic approaches to
improve the verification process.
>> Yes.
>> Do they control the amount of test
compute?
Um
I I believe so. You mean test s times
when they're using the verifier like a
baseline verifier versus themselves? I
I'm actually not sure if they do they do
that when they're doing process versus
because again that's really hard to do
like but
>> you're scaling things right.
>> Yeah. I think that could actually be a
question that you could investigate like
you can sample more on the generator,
you could sample more on the verifier if
you if you're controlling for a fixed
compute. How do you allocate that? Um so
one of the challenges here is that
usually like the OM and PM should come
from the same data for us to do like a
good like apples to apples comparison,
right? Um cuz if you do train a PRM and
someone else train an RM makes things a
bit harder. The training data also
matters a lot.
>> Any other questions? Yes.
>> Um, can you go back to the 3D slide?
>> No, I was just Oh, no. No. It was the
basically for this one I was just
curious as to why after using RL um they
stuck with evaluating performances with
3D decoding. Uh I was just curious like
whether or not you know raising the
temperature like really made a
difference or that's the only way they
could have seen like the you know
smalish delta.
So the the the reason so the question is
why they they stopped greedy decoding
why they didn't do like temperature
changes and test time scaling again
right I think that's what this slide is
so they they then in this case
um the verification is done against 256
outputs so the previous one is um no
verification right the ver verifier is
just using the RL training here it is at
test time as well Yeah,
I think it's something that they didn't
do and it would be interesting to see
what if they repeat the process again
um generate another set of labels and
train a verifier and then but starting
from this RLPPO
model. Yeah.
>> Okay. Let's get to the last paper. um
shrinking the generation verification
gap with weak verifiers. So this is the
paper a paper um that uh from from
Stanford that uh came out a couple of
months ago at this point. So um it's a
new 2025 paper. So the motivation again
um is
the same. We have we still have a
generation verification gap and but the
approach here was a bit different. The
here we were not training a new
verifier. We were thinking can we reduce
the generation verification gap by using
inference compute and inference scaling
and specifically by using an ensemble of
verifiers because it's but when we say
weak we just assume that no verifier is
perfect. So that's the weakness. We
didn't purposefully choose like bad
verifiers. These are the best verifiers
that are out there, but we are using an
ensemble of them to create uh a single
uh much more capable verifier. Um
so the property of weak verifiers is
that they do have they do correlate with
the true label of the problem but they
have of the solution but they have
imperfections. Um and there are two
types of these verifiers. We learned
about PRM and OMS. But another one that
we briefly discussed in the in in a few
minutes ago is that we can use LLMs
themselves as a judge. We can show it an
answer and ask it whether do you think
this is correct or not. The prompt could
be literally that or we can have the
model use tools and use rubrics and all
that to uh generate a score for a model.
So that's a whole category of verifiers
that we can use on top of just PRMs and
OMS. Um so here this first graph just
shows um how ensembling and using a
number of verifiers that are they could
be trained by different labs on
different data sets. We just like and
there are all these language models that
take a query as input and give a score
at on the output side. Here we are
comparing uh we are seeing these four
data sets. So in this case we showing
the performance of top one versus top
five versus top 10 verifiers based on
like how good they are in some ranking
system. Overall, it seems like um
like just uh un ensembling them with
each other um and using them at test
time
uh does improve things u but not in a
necessarily in a monotonically monotonic
way. But the thing that always helped
was that if we train a model to a a way
for them to to add them together. to
assign weights for different members of
the ensemble if we have labels from
them. Here we have we have two methods
naive base or logistic regression. These
are very simple methods. Basically, you
add a simple single weight per verifier
to score them together to and if you
have a training set set for for your
with a with labels, you can basically
come up with these weights and and now
these results are on the test set
corresponding to those tasks. So, you
basically say for math 500 500 I have a
set of labels. I use that to average my
verifiers, find the weights and then I
use this averages on a new on test data.
So that does give it seems like it does
give a lot lot of improvement just this
simple task. Um now you can do other
things. So the the way we works is by
this score weight and select approach.
So in the first step, we are going to
score outputs of the verifiers and uh
normalize them so they're all on the
same scale and and um and filter out the
lowquality verifier. So in this setup
even we are assuming we have access to a
very limited labels that we can say okay
these verifiers are just so bad against
our labels we just remove them from our
ensemble. We have noticed that this is a
very important step like your verifiers
should be above a certain quality to be
even be let in the pool of verifiers. So
then you have your verifiers, you have
your LM judges, you have your reward
models and then you get these scores
from them whether it's zero or one or
the log prop of correctness per um per
verifier. And then um what weieber did
was to use weak su weak supervision to
uh estimate kind of the verifier
accuracy with very small uh data labeled
data and then um and then we use those
ways to combine the verifiers output and
assign a score. Um I go briefly through
like how this week to strong supervision
works. Some of you if you have t taken
deep learning courses or even CS 229s
last time we talked about it about weak
to strong supervision. There's a whole
body of work here. Uh beaver was
specifically u kind of uh
um motivated by the work by snorkel by
Alex ran ratnell atal and other work
from Stanford. So the so here is how we
have these weak verifiers like weak
signal from our verifiers and combine
them together to get a stronger signal.
The setup is the following. We have n
queries. For each query we create k
solutions and then let's assume we have
m verifiers. So we have a total of n * k
* m labels. uh and our goal here is to
create to get this probability of um
query I sample J uh equal to one given
all the labels that we get from all the
verifiers. So how do we estimate this
probability correctly? Um the assumption
in beaver is that each verifier captures
independent aspect of the correctness.
So this is a key assumption that we
made. Um to some extent the reason we
get so think about it this way if you
have a pool of verifiers if all of them
agree on the score that they give to any
sample then we are not learning anything
new from them right if all of them are
like 100% or the same score the signal
here is on kind of similarity and
dissimilarity across these whole set of
verifiers with each other. So under this
assumption we can write this probability
for the the response being correct given
the labels that we have and then we use
two sets of equations. Again this the
first equation uh is uh we can write it
this way because we assume every two
verifier I and J are independent from
each other. The second equation is the
the just the base uh kind of the the the
way probability works. There's no
assumption in writing this. And given
these two uh we can kind of define uh we
can write an optimization and def come
up with the weights that we can assign
to each of the the verifiers.
Um and here we are comparing the results
with a naive ensemble approach. And it
turns out that it does help in some
cases that the the gains are more
significant in GPQA diamond um and math
and ML MMLU pro and each of these
problems that are relatively hard uh
problems for example the GPQA are our
our baseline um is already low but the
very fire this way of weak to strong
aggregation of uh responses is helping
getting a large boost over naive
ensemble. ing of them. Um, now there are
different ways that we can scale the
verification compute. We can sample more
generations. So instead of 10 samples,
we can do a 100 or a thousand. We can
use larger models for generation and
verification. We can increase the the
number of verifiers in the pool. um uh
and and in general there are different
ways to assign flops or inference uh
scale inference compute for um for
solving a problem. Um here we are
comparing uh some of these methods with
each other. So the dashed uh kind of
dark red line is the passetk oracle
meaning that if we had like an oracle
uh selector that would give us the
correct answer. We don't have that and
that's why we are training these
verifiers. Um the the purple one is we
were supervised and that's assumed that
we have a large body of label data and
we can use them to learn these weights.
The blue one is the unsupervised. In
this case, we're using 1% of the
training labels for each data set. Um
the orange one is the naive ensemble,
meaning we just average them average the
on the the the verifiers without any
special treatment. We still are
filtering um and keeping the good
verifiers in the loop. And then all of
these are significantly better than
methods such as majority voting or
multi- aent verification. And
multi-agent verification just or MAV is
um it's just based on prompting LLMs and
asking them to score a given response
based on different kind of aspects that
is produced. So kind of a rubric base
which is doesn't do that that much
better or actually worse in these two
cases than majority voting.
Um but something to notice here is the
drastic gains that the model can have
going from something like 40 less like
slightly over 40% to over 70% on these
hard uh problems. and in this case
matching a model like 03 mini. Um so the
thing that is interesting here is that
the we can use this weak to super weak
to strong supervision to reduce the gap
between model classes. So what we are
saying here is that if we take a
generator model of llama 3.18b instruct
and the verifier um model which is like
the the pool of verifiers that are 8b
and below uh we get an average of 70% on
these data set and this is almost
comparable to the accuracy that we get
with majority voting but when our models
and uh models are at 7B. So we are kind
of like
making the model making this 8B model
um the same roughly the same as the 7TB
class by just doing this inference
scaling and using the verifier and in
this case unlike the what we saw in most
of the previous lecture we are talking
about the end results we're not talking
about the coverage we're talking about
the solution accuracy of the entire
system.
Um and here again in this case for when
we do the same apply the same generation
and verification to 70B class of models
we are getting an average accuracy of
86.2% 2% on these data sets and this is
very comparable to this to O3 mini which
um which has a much uh uh which is like
a proprietary model and in general is a
higher like a different class of models.
So this shows how much verification or
this work on verification can help with
the results. Um, another uh work that
was done on the increasing the
usefulness of something like Vaver is
that a challenge with ensembling
verifiers is that you have a ton of like
models that now you need to run for each
solution to get a score and then to
average them, right? To uh and that
increases the cost especially if you
instead of one sample per per you have a
100 samples and then you want to create
all these scores. So instead what uh the
proposal here is that what if we do
train wever once and then distill it
into a much smaller model um and that's
how instead of running each of these LLM
judges or reward models per sample we
just take this distilled uh LM which in
this case we show that it could be
really really tiny like something like
400 million parameters as opposed to the
original model which was in the 70B
range. Um, and it turns out that with
this distilled model, we can kind of
capture 97% of accuracy of this large
pool of L uh verifiers, but be
significantly in this case 99 plus% use
less compute at test time. And these uh
and these um distilled version and the
original version, they're all open
sourced and the checkpoints are
available. um if any of you are
interested in working with them in your
um agentic or test time scaling
projects.
Um
and here is another graph. Here is the
distilled one which is the light blue
one and the original beaver is the dark
blue one. And we are comparing again the
efficiency the success rate over the
inference compute the total inference
compute that we are spending on this
data set. Um and u
um and the distilled one obviously is
like significantly more efficient. uh
but even the original weaver because it
reaches higher levels of accuracy um at
those levels it becomes more flop
efficient than models like naive
ensemble and majority voting
and
let's do a quick recap. So um here we
today we covered like four papers that
also showed the trajectory of how this
work on verific how research on
verification has progressed over the
last like four years. We talked about
how verification
um can improve training both during uh
can improve the outcome of the and the
quality of results uh both uh during
training and inference. uh process
rewards seems to be very useful and
overall uh very effective uh and more so
than the outcome rewards but perhaps we
need to combine them to get the best
results both PRMS and OMS um and we also
in Matt Shepard learned that scaling you
need a lot of data and the more data you
throw in the verifier training it
becomes better and you can use it during
your RL uh fine-tuning to increase the
quality of your generator as well. And
uh the beaver work was took a whole
different approach to verification was
and that was just uh doing this weak
supervised optimization on an ensemble
of verifiers and in a way we are using
test time scaling but by bringing more
verifiers rather than sampling a single
verifier more um to to get the results
and we can turns out we can distill that
and capture a whole lot of the quality
uh from a much smaller model and With
that I can conclude the class. Any
questions?
Yes.
>> The papers were on math or reasoning uh
benchmarks. Do you think there's
anything else that [clears throat] could
work for project other ways to evaluate
the model?
>> Um like coding other ways to evaluate
the model. You mean other areas like
coding would be a very interesting uh
area for for reasoning. So these like
there were like some coding problems in
this CT like in some of the benchmarks
here. So it's not not just math uh but
um coding is also a very interesting
kind of uh area for verification. We
will uh we will talk about code monkeys.
This is a paper uh that instead of
directly training a verifier, you can
make the model create a test time system
to make the model generate unit tests
and those unit tests become your
verifier. So that's an entire different
approach. Um but these kind of
verifications should also be useful for
any kind of reasoning task.
>> Yes. I'm curious like how do generation
verification help
us model like that internalized
one.
>> Okay. So the question is that for
reasoning model how does the generation
verification or these kind of test time
scalings work for them? It actually
helps them as well still. uh but the
reasoning model like uh we're going to
talk about them in this class but
basically what they're doing a big part
of it is to generate these reasoning
steps use the reward for it and do an RL
loop and generate positive trajectories
and then use that positive trajectories
as part of training for the next round.
Right? So the test time scaling is
inherently used to generate data and
generate the training process. But they
still would benefit because they still
uh could explore different parts of the
solution space with with more sampling
kind of like knowledge using training on
the test. Do you think in the future
like this two parish or do you think
like um maybe like repeat sampling would
only be used for generating training for
>> Yes. So the question is like would we
converge to a future where these kind of
test time scaling repeated sampling and
science just for training time to create
the data and then at test time we uh we
just use ask the model once I think
that's the direction we want to go right
we want the model to be really really
good at pass at one like the first time
we ask it to do something we want it to
generate and that increases the
efficiency and all that like that would
be the hope one challenge though with
making the model too like like to make
the the log props of the model too
sharpened through through one answer is
that the creativity and diversity of
solutions may be lost some somehow
during the training. Um so
surprisingly we still like them like
models that are very d like create have
a lot of creativity and diversity in the
way that they they think and that's like
a good feature that we want to have in
the models.
>> Yes.
Does it matter if generator and
verifiers have very different
architectures? For example, if the
verifier is like a mini version of the
generator versus if they're very
different architectures,
>> but does it matter like like which one
which one is um empirically?
>> Okay, so the question is like if the
generator and verifier from the same
family or not. That's that's a good
research question. Um I think in general
it's interesting like models like their
own generations and their their own way
of interpreting results much better than
using a different family of models. Um
we are going to talk about a paper that
talks about how uh certain models can
benefit from like a different class of
verifiers over themselves. But like a
specifically uh I am unaware of a study
that has looked into that specific
question of uh same kind of size and
family versus uh different size
different family. How does how that
changes the behavior of the model?